Commission on Adult Basic Education (COABE) Records
Commission on Adult Basic Education (COABE) Records
1955-2008
1990-2004
Commission on Adult Basic Education (U.S.)
4 linear ft..
Records and papers of the adult education and literacy organization. Collection includes conference planning and programs, minutes, published material, newsletters, membership directories, policies and procedures, bylaws, treasurer's reports, strategic planning files, historian reports, more.
2684651
Biographical History
The purpose of the Commission on Adult Basic Education (COABE) is to advance national and international adult education and literacy opportunities. It promotes, advocates for, and conducts literacy and lifelong education efforts. COABE was formed in 1971 to represent non-public adult education and literacy programs within the Adult Education Association (AEA) (public adult education and literacy programs were represented by the National Association for Public Continuing Adult Education, or NAPCAE). In 1982 NAPCAE and AEA merged to create the American Association for Adult Continuing Education (AAACE), and in 1999 COABE formally split from AAACE to become an independent organization.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Commission on Adult Basic Education (COABE) Records are subdivided into general files and financial files.
General files contains agenda and minutes from board meetings, correspondence, conference planning and programs, Historian's reports and essays, legislative reports, photographs, and other items relating to the functioning of the organization. Of particular interest here is the material preceding COABE's separation from AAACE ("AAACE/COABE relationship"), and material dating from 2008 in which COABE explored a merger with ProLiteracy Worldwide. The Historian folder also contains essays by Albert Campbell, COABE historian, including a brief history of the organization.
Financial files contains budget reports, scholarship and grant information, and paperwork relating to the establishment of an endowment.
Arrangement of the Collection
Material are arranged roughly alphabetically with the two main series.
Related Material
has numerous collections in the area of adult education; please refer to for a complete listing. For COABE material in particular, see also the
Adult Education Association/American Association for Adult and Continuing Education Records
,
Drew Allbritten Papers
,
William Langner Papers
, and
William S. Griffith Papers
.
Subject and Genre Headings
Adult education; Commission on Adult Basic Education (U.S.); Adult education -- United States.; Educators -- United States.; Elementary education of adults.; Agendas (administrative records); Annual reports.; Articles.; Budgets.; Constitutions.; Correspondence.; Directories.; Manuals (instructional materials); Memorandums.; Minutes (administrative records); Reports.; Speeches (documents); Educators.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Albert Campbell, COABE Historian, 2009.
Inventory
- General records
  - AEA [Adult Education Association] Annual Reports, 1979; 1980 (Box 1)
  - Awards, 1989-2005 (Box 1)
  - Agenda/minutes
    - 1980-1999 (Box 1)
    - 2000-2008 (Box 2)
  - AAACE/COABE relationships, 1992-1998 (Box 2)
  - Conference planning and evaluation, 1977; 1992,; 1993,; 1996,; 1997,; 1998,; 2002,; 2008 (Box 2)
  - Conference programs
    - 1976, 1980, 1985, 1987-1991 (Box 2)
    - 1992-2000 (Box 3)
    - 2001-2006 (Box 4)
  - Conference reports, 1977-1979; 1985,; 1987,; 1992-2005; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Conference site selection guidelines, 1990; 1995,; undated (Box 5)
  - Conference miscellany, 1990-1996; undated (Box 5)
  - Correspondence, 1988-2001 (Box 5)
  - Elections, 1992-1998; undated (Box 5)
  - Historian, 1997-2005; includes several essays by Albert Campbell, COABE Historian, such as "Where Have You Gone, Malcolm Knowles: Adult Education and Baseball" (1999) and "A Brief History of the National Commission on Adult Basic Education" (2002) (Box 5)
  - Journal, circa 1993-2008; information on Adult Basic Education, published by COABE; 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Leadership, officers, 1979-2008; includes a 3.5" floppy disk, unknown format (Box 6)
  - Legislative reports, 1995-1998 (Box 6)
  - Membership, 1989-2003; 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Newsletter, 1976; 1992-2008 (Box 6)
  - Photographs (Box 7)
  - Planning and strategic plan, 1979-1980; 1994,; 1996-2005,; undated; 3 folders (Box 7)
  - Policies and procedures (Box 7)
  - Pro-Literacy, 2000-2008 (Box 7)
  - Publicity, 1993; for 1993 conference (Box 7)
  - Technology reports, 2005 (Box 7)
- Financial papers
  - Budget, 1995-1997 (Box 8)
  - Budget reports, 1992-2005 (Box 8)
  - Endowment, 1996-1998 (Box 8)
  - Scholarship, grants (Box 8)
  - Treasurer's reports, 1955-2006 (Box 8)